so this is majima nikai 20 with santana
which is
the five strategies
for bringing unwholesome thought to its
rest so um
so um
this is um this is how we chose to
translate this title
and um
so the suture goes by
saying uh here because when a biku is
giving attention to some sign
owing to that sign
there arise in him evil unwholesome
thoughts connected with desire with hate
with delusion
then he should give attention to some
other sign connected with what's
wholesome connected with what's um
connected with what's um
uh with what's wholesome with what's
connected with non-desire non-hate and
non-delusion so when he gives attention to some other
so when he gives attention to some other
sign connected what is wholesome the
evil unwholesome thoughts connected with
desire with hate with delusion or
abandoning him and subside
with the abandoning of them his mind
becomes steadied internally quieted and
brought to singleness and composed
he says just as a skilled carpenter or
his apprentice might knock out to remove
and extract a course peg by means of a
fine one
so we spoke about the signs of the mind
before um so maybe we should not get into it
um so maybe we should not get into it
now
we're trying to link the talk to the
what signs of the mind are the point is
so it's not just it's not about the
objects of your senses
of your senses
it's not about um
[Music] it's not even about the specific
it's not even about the specific
thoughts you might have
it's about the signs of the mind in
regards so it's about a state of the
mind that you are in that is then exemplified
that you are in that is then exemplified
uh through thoughts that are revolving
revolving uh in your head so to speak
so in this case it's the state of mind
that that is affected with desire hate
or delusion
so
you can know what state of mind you have
on account of what thoughts are are
popping up persisting and pressuring you
so the point here is to to see that the
problem is not on the level of the
thoughts the problems on the level of
the state of mind behind so that's why
then you recognize that hold on i don't
need to battle and fight these thoughts
that are sailing me right here right now
stop them from my mind from thinking all
i need to do is direct that mind to to
to it's a different theme
and then these thoughts will will be
replaced because it's the theme of the
mind the state of the mind the context
the peripheral as you often say
that's that's what determines what
thoughts would be coming up for you what
thoughts would be arising and and
persisting and increasing and pressuring
you um
um
so that's the first way the second way
he says
if he's giving attention to some other
sign connected what is wholesome
they're in uh they're still these these
evil and wholesome states still
possessed they don't go away
uh then he should examine the danger in
those thoughts so so basically then he
should start again seeing the danger
of that state of mind
that is exemplified through these
thoughts so
am i welcoming the thoughts of of say
ill will
am i am i am i um
accepting them mentally and allowing my
mind to revolve around them even further
and if so then you should start
contemplating danger in doing that very
thing so it's not about seeing the danger in
so it's not about seeing the danger in
the thoughts that arise on their own or
something that just appear no it's
seeing the danger in you accepting them
welcoming them delighting in them and
acting out of them
so that that can then help
so and then the similarly is just as it
says just as a man or a woman young
youthful fond of ornaments would be
horrified humiliated and disgusted if
the carcass of a snake or a dog or a
human being were hung around his or her
neck so that's that's that you should be
so that's that's that you should be
disgusted and horrified by
by your choice of entertainment
of such thoughts of anger or lust and so
on not horrified and discussed by
an object of a thought in itself that
has appeared on its own so to speak
because that's not your responsibility
your responsibility and the disgust
should come from the recognition that
you are the one accepting this and
welcoming it and delighting in it
or in other words practically speaking
am i
consciously am i choosing am i saying
yes to the pressure to
to the pressure to
resolve these thoughts
and get involved with them
so so what i'm referring to it's like um
say you do have a mind
that that doesn't want to let go of
something and your thoughts are
pressuring you and the mind is just
revolving around it and the thoughts are
just popping up and going
uh you want to get rid of the discomfort
of that say somebody upset you you're
angry so it's unpleasant so usually
people go about get getting rid of that
by acting out
saying something harming the other and
then feeling satisfied on account of it
but fundamentally the problem was
you refused to bear the discomfort of
that state of mind
now say on the other hand you don't
quite act out of it physically you don't
act out you don't do anything bad and
unwholesome uh verbally either but
mentally you are still choosing you know there's
you are still choosing you know there's
like a
imagine like well you don't imagine just
remember last time you had like a like a
a compulsive type of
thinking pressuring in your mind
revolving around it
um when the
you know there might be like a sort of
like like a spike in the pressure and so
on and then you're enduring it and
thoughts are sort of popping up and in
trying to make you act but then there's
always a time when you
willingly kind of
bitterly almost accept
and and then plunge yourself further in
those thoughts yeah but still and then
you carry on and then sure then you
can't stop it because you gave it the
momentum but then again the momentum starts
but then again the momentum starts
fading away because it will go as far as
you pushed it previously but it's
usually people kind of don't even
recognize the fact that they were the
one pushing it every now and then they
were the one adding fuel to the fire
every now and then so then all they see
is wow this momentum never stops and i'm
fully subject to it and i don't know
what to do how to stop this mind from
thinking these thoughts
all you need to do is
not not make those better choices
those little subtle
yeah okay i'll just give in to resolve
this thought that bothers me
and then be patient
and it will have to run its course
and then you know there might be some
like a
more ambiguous pressure trying to make
you pick it up again
but unless you're careless and unless
you or or unless you willingly choose to
pick it up again it cannot pick itself
up
and that's th that's the important point
here so number three
uh if while he's examining the danger in
those thoughts those thoughts are still
not resting they're not put to rest
then he should try to uh ignore him so
he should not give attention to those
thoughts so he should recognize and
that's kind of on the level seeing the
mind as mine seeing the state of the
mind regardless of what thoughts are
there coming or going
so
first you just tried okay thoughts are
there well they're unwholesome
well they're unwholesome
let me let me
contemplate the more wholesome theme
that can then change the state of this
mind that revolves around these thoughts
and then hopefully these thoughts will
go away so if that fails then you look
for the danger in in accepting those
thoughts so then they will go away
because you stopped accepting them you
stop welcoming them in
but now if that doesn't work either then
just ignore the thoughts and stay
mindful of off your mind just stay
mindful of the state of the mind and
again see the danger is kind of
still seen he might not be helping you
um for these thoughts to to leave you
alone but nevertheless the dangerous
scene which means
if you just stay mindful
of the state of the mind so if the signs
of your mind
that that reveal what state is in so you
you should just use that as a container
so you know like i don't need to worry
about the specific thoughts as long as i
stay uh uh
recollected
within this state of mind that induced
for as long as endured i won't do
anything polish i won't do anything
stupid i won't do anything careless and
then these thoughts because now you're
really not paying any attention to them so to
not paying any attention to them so to
speak you are
concerned with the state of the mind and
state of the mind alone
those thoughts could hopefully go away
or go to rest
number four
if while ignoring and trying to forget
those thoughts
um and not giving attention to them
still unwholesome thoughts arise
then he should give attention to
stealing the thought formation
of those thoughts um
um
and when he gives attention to still in
the thought formation so the thought
activity the activation how we translate it then
the activation how we translate it then
any unwholesome thoughts connected with
desire with
hate and delusion would be abandoned and
just subside
so
with abandoning them his mind becomes
steady internally quieted brought to
singleness and composed just as a man
walking fast might consider why am i
walking fast what if i walk slowly if
you walk slowly then you might consider
why i'm walking slowly but if i stand if
he would stand then he might consider
why am i standing what if i sit and then
if he would sit he might consider one
was sitting what if i lay down
by doing so he would substitute each
grocery posture for one there was
subtler so that this pertains basically to the
so that this pertains basically to the
um
the activity the thought formation
the the thought sankara the center of
your thoughts so so the activity of your
thoughts it's like um
so
you are not as i said as i often say
um you don't have to worry about
the actual uh thought in itself being
present but see the activity of a
thought is something you're already engaged with
is something you're already engaged with
just as i added earlier it's that like
for example one of the activity there
would be
fueling one there will be forming your
thoughts further
is that uh that choice that one would
make um towards uh
um towards uh
[Music]
resolving a thought or dealing with it
or addressing it or whatever so so
the uh the coarseness of that choice
would be the strength of the activity
so if you're like really just keep
picking it up
um
and and in that in that like a better
way that offers you a possibility of but
it will resolve itself if i just keep
you know if i go back to one more time
and and and address this thought and address
and and address this thought and address
that and who said what and when and how
and um it's that's that's the that's that uh
um it's that's that's the that's that uh
the activities that you can start
refining you really well wait what if i
just don't do this choice and then like
endure the pressure of choosing instead
of enduring the pressure of uh thoughts
that have been chosen and now revolving
out of your control
and then that choice can be refined
further and further and further
and that's that recognition but mind you
this is not something you could just
do first this is when all the other
things fail which means you were able to
successfully do all the other things
beforehand you were you know how to not pay
you were you know how to not pay
attention to thoughts you are skilled in
seeing the signs of your mind and see
the state of the mind but yes
if you fulfill those previous three
steps methods um
the time will come when some thoughts
would still persist because they are
subtler dead more deeply rooted and so
on and then you actually have to
deactivate them let's say like that
deactivate them by by refining your
involvement with those thoughts
so the reason why i'm pointing this out
is because again somebody reads this
image like they might think oh these are
just like five ways and i'll pick and
choose and do this sometimes and do that
sometimes sure if you're skilled in all
five you can do that but there is a
reason that they're listed in this order
there's a reason that the buddha doesn't
start telling somebody yeah calm your
mind by stealing the thought formation
because you know what will they make of
it
um
so if if you are already familiar with
the nature of you know pressuring
thoughts not welcoming not delighting
ignoring them when necessary not
forgetting the state of mind in other
words if you have
trained yourself uh long enough in
enduring thoughts without acting out of
them the time will come when you're
gonna start recognizing these more
subtler uh
uh
forms of your engagement with your own
thinking like how you're taking it up
let's say like that
and then you reckon wait a minute so
what if i don't take it up in this
manner what if i don't take up this
thinking as much
and then it is oh that's all it was
enough for this thought to be put to
rest it's it's it's specifically a a
thought activation a thought sankara
so things that are basically keeping the
thoughts active let's say like that and
those things it's exactly welcoming
delighting uh entertaining not seeing
the danger
all of those are your attitudes your
ways coarse ways or coarser ways of
taking up those very thoughts
um so
if you have been training the previous
three ways
and enduring the thought sufficiently
enough not acting out of them you're
gonna start seeing uh uh these this
subtle attitude there's something that
oh
or or rather let's say like you're gonna
find yourself doing or holding these
attitudes so you're not going to see the
attitude sort of oh look i chose it and
it came to be you will find yourself
delighting in a thought but when you do
that would be enough to stop delighting
then you might find yourself in a course
closely sort of
uh gripped by whatever revolving around
and taking up and trying to deal with
something trying to get rid of trying to
manage it and then you catch yourself up
you catch that attitude behind those
thoughts behind your involvement with
them and when you do catch that attitude
then it will uh it will that will be
enough to drop it
and then if even that doesn't work and
the thoughts are still pressuring you
and the enduring of them is still
unpleasant the fifth way is just bear it
you you did all you can now you just
have to bear until these thoughts go
away on their own
uh with his teeth clenched in tongue
press against the roof of his mouth he
should beat down constrain and crush the
mind with the mind so you just basically
take on the state of mind whichever way
it is and you just say no and and do it
and do it kicking and screaming until it
calms down
so buried
and then
the simile is uh just as a strong man
might see the weaker man by the head or
shoulders and beat him down constrain
him and crush him
um
with his teeth clenching he's talked
that that's how he should do it to his
mind until that mind becomes studied
internally quieted and brought to
singleness so these are the ways of the five ways
so these are the ways of the five ways
of resting the thoughts it's not they're
not the five ways of getting rid of the
thoughts because again that's that's
that's predicated on a view that
uh thoughts in themselves are the
problem no it's the pressure behind the
thoughts and that pressure behind the
thoughts that you have to endure is due
to your state of mind towards those
thoughts so there are few uh
so there are few uh
statements and questions regarding this
passages we just read
um
so there seems to be a difference
between thought and thinking um
as in a thought is a kind of intentional
mental image that one can choose to
think about or not
a thought arises and exerts pressure on
me to think it yeah yeah you can say
that so and that's what i mean the thought
so and that's what i mean the thought
presents itself
and it can reveal the underlying problem if
it can reveal the underlying problem if
there is one so you wouldn't have a
thought infused with sensual desire
without a mind that's already leaning
towards sensuality thought in itself is
not a problem but yes what you then keep
choose to think around it
through either your attitude of i must
get rid of this because it bothers me i
need more of this because it pressures
me
and so on that's now your involvement
and your responsibility and that's
really the problem
so
the second question is these
instructions seem to be the five ways of
enduring a thought
so as to remove the fuel that sustains
the unwholesome thought yeah exactly so
that fuel brings one direct interference
with it by the way of denial resistance
acceptance exactly yeah that's the
simile we often say it's like you know
somebody comes at your door starts
yelling or screaming or trying to seduce
you to get out and all of that
you might think that's a problem and
then you open the door and you get out
and get uninvolved get into a fight or
chase them or follow them and you're
just oh no the problem is basically all
they want is to get you out of the house
that's it that's the problem
so it doesn't matter how how much
they're in front of your door and how
often they pressure you unless you
choose to open that door unless you
choose to get involved on that level of
the mind
then you'll be there there will be no
problems so that's not to say that you know when
so that's not to say that you know when
the mind revolves around a certain
you know thing he can't it can can't let
go so it's just it's just it's just
revolving he's just revolving he's just
revolving it's not that you choose to do that
it's not that you choose to do that
that's the symptom
of you basically not seeing the signs of
your mind correctly
so i'm qualifying this because sometimes
a person might think okay so i will not
open the door
and uh and all this kind of compulsive
thinking will stop on its own
uh well yes if you correctly not open
the door that will happen but the
problem is first you need to see the
door well and in order to see the door
you need to see the signs that point
where that door is you need to recognize
the state of mind regardless of the
thoughts that that are kind of
pressuring and revolving in front of you
and that's the point usually when the
mind is gripped by something
say again some some some compulsive
theme that you can't let go of whatever
it might be
your attitude is
implying that it's the thinking that's
the problem and that's why you're not
seeing where the mind is because your
mind basically is implying that it's
there the problem is there it's not
don't look here look over there that's
where the problem is and then the more
you look at the thoughts the more you
fuel them
because you're obviously way out the
door wide open and then and then you
don't even see the mind so that's why i
always say that that endurance not
welcome and not acting out that has to
come first which means you're gonna
probably have quite a few episodes of
compulsively neurotically mind revolving
around stuff and he won't listen to you
and he won't drop it and you realize
okay so basically i need to endure it
until it tires out and that's all the
similarities the buddha was talking
about you know in reference to taming
the mind like getting a wild elephant
and you don't get a wild elephant and
immediately start issuing commands it's
just it doesn't work you get a wild
elephant you know chain it put the put the chain
you know chain it put the put the chain
in in a strong peg in the ground and
then just wait until it completely gets
tired from kicking and screaming which
is what it's going to do
so
another reason why this is important to
keep in mind is because people will
easily assume that these five ways of
resting or making your thoughts rest or
dealing with the thoughts are applicable
on the level of that compulsive thinking
no if there is a compulsive thinking
going on
means oh you are fully griped by it
there is no signs of the mind that are
being noticed because that's what feeds
the compulsion so you recognize the
compulsion is the symptom then of me not
seeing what i need to see and in order
to do it i need to wait for this to to
tie itself out
and then you recognize what thoughts are
rising persisting what are pressuring
you and then you can even foresee them
before they actually are fully
actualized in that sense
so so another way like i think before
any of these five ways become applicable
a person needs to do a great deal of
endurance of their own thoughts and
their own mind without acting out of it
or without trying to get rid of it
so these are non-methods of getting rid
of the thoughts
their methods of of taming your mind third statement
third statement
in brief it seems to me that
one leaves the thought alone while doing
something else which indirectly results
in unwholesome thought
which is persisting in the background
dying out
it's like trying to remove an unwanted
guest
guest without any indication to him that
you're doing so
because if he notices that you're trying
to remove him he stays longer or just
pretends to leave
just so that he can return later to what
you struggle again yeah i i think you
can say that it's it's uh
if you go head-on
against these thoughts as i said means
are you basically off of you your mind
is of an implication that that's where
the problem is and that's it you
acknowledged you acknowledged the fact
that you were affected by the pressure
of the thoughts and that's all the
thoughts want
so whether you try to get rid of them or
say yes to them the point is you are
fueling them so exactly so how do you
get rid of them without making them know
you're trying to get rid of them well by
first not showing signs of of any
disturbance on account of their presence
so no matter how close they get you you
learn how to operate without acting out
without kicking screaming without you
know trying to push them away and so on
and then they can't see that you're
affected and then you can actually start
operating within that that will be well
you will become invisible let's say like
that to them so then you can actually
you can deal with them properly
these strategies are the middleweight
practices yes
and thus they're quite subtle yes
they help you endure the pressure of the
unwholesome and in doing so deep
pressure the situation but no longer
contributing towards it exactly yeah
because the the pressure say unwanted
guest back to the just the recent simile
the pressure there is not the uh it's
not the guest
it's you
resisting the discomfort of that guest
that's why you're pressured
and so so if you
learn how to depressurize yourself
for like a better word um regardless of
whether there's a guest there or trying
to enter this on you'll be at peace no
problem
um there's a like a longer question i
used to i used to try to get rid of last
little thinking by doing various things
like a super contemplation cold showers
mowing the lawn and so on
and although it worked in the beginning
i still on
the later occasions gave into lustful
thinking which meant that i had to do a
subar and everything else again
i realized that this would go on forever
and that was as you say not dealing with
the roots of the problem but only with
its symptoms yeah exactly so
so
it's it's management it's what we often
say in the in many other talks like
uprooting versus management that's
that's the fundamental difference here
and again bear that in mind even when
you read this pseudo paragraph this is
not management this is uprooting
so you're not just
trying to get rid of these thoughts
because they bother me no you're trying
to basically
uproot the state of the mind that makes
these thoughts bother you and keep
coming back for you so i find that major
monika 20
seems to give strategies in dealing with
the roots of the problem and not the
symptom one could use the strategies to
deal with its symptoms but eventually
one's energy would run out because one
is unknowingly still fueling the
thoughts which inevitably bring about
the thinking yeah that's that's the
whole the similar of the trap you know you
the similar of the trap you know you
think like i must deal with this thought
but oh and thought presents itself as
something no listen if you deal with
this if you follow this desire you'll be
satisfied if you you know get rid of
this discomfort you know if you're a
virgin everything will be fall back into
place that's how the thought presents itself
that's how the thought presents itself
that's why it traps you and lures you
out but really all the thought wants to do
but really all the thought wants to do
is for you to to acknowledge it to
acknowledge it in a sense
uh through to denying it again in order
to deny something you need to you need
to recognize it you need to act out
towards it or to affirm it or even to
like um
just um
be delusional about it let's say like
that not even know where the problem is
so the last point is for the one who
applies these strategies on the right
level one must be able to discern the
signs of the mind the cheetah nimita
intentions before and behind one's
actions by taking the fuel away from the
by taking the fuel away from the
unwholesome intentions one will not have
to deal with the unwholesome thinking
yeah so that that's kind of sums it up
it's the the fuel so it's the five ways
of uh unplugging
the the energy that fuels your your your
thoughts of the unwholesome kind yeah and then
of the unwholesome kind yeah and then
the buddha finishes by saying if you
know if a monk
with the right view
uh correctly practices all of this um
he'll be the master of his thoughts
he'll be able to think whatever he wants
to think and not think whatever he
doesn't want to think
in other words
his mind will be completely tamed and
his mind will obey his will it will
listen to him
it will do what he tells it to do